Okay, so we want to compute the average duration of employment.
Well, that's going to be easy.
If we do basically a version of the same calculation that we did before,
we're going to find the average duration of staying employed is now one over beta.
It's exactly the same that we did before, except in this case p is going to be beta.
So in our in our in our in our lake model, we have that one over alpha is the average
average duration of unemployment.
And one over beta is the average duration of employment.
And we got that from the from just the parameters that define the transition model.
Just mentioned another example, which is a classic example of a mark off chain.
So quite a famous paper by James Hamilton for using US unemployment data.
So he was looking at unemployment data too.
He estimated a stochastic matrix.
Now you know what that is from our definition.
So he estimated this econometrically.
Later on we'll talk about how you might go around estimating this.
So he estimated with monthly data and he had three states.
He had what he called a normal growth state.
A mild recession and a severe recession.
He estimated this some time ago.
Before he actually had data on what we in the United States now regard as severe recessions.
So you know what the these transition probabilities are interesting because they tell you like.
Well when when you're in normal growth we can just read this.
When you're normal growth they usually just stay in the most likely thing is you'll stay in normal growth.
But with the small probability you'll go into like we growth.
So you know if you're in we growth.
So you'll you'll stay there for an experience.
You might go back to normal growth but there's a very small probability that you'll go to a very bad growth state.
Big recession.
And if you have the unfortunate to get to a bad growth state you're never going back from there to.
To high growth right away.
You might you might transit to a.
Well if you're not I'm reading it wrong.
If you're if you're in a very bad growth state.
You you might recover to a slightly less bad growth state but you won't go all the way back you won't go back here.
So these things that I was just struggling to explain.
People write down what's called a directed graph.
And a directed graph has a consists of nodes.
And edges.
It's a very nice way to describe a mark off chain.
If you wake a pdf you'll find that.
So let's see what it looks like.
So this is a typical directed graph to to show Hamilton's.
This is Hamilton's.
Model for mark off model for unemployment.
So this is normal growth.
So what this arrow means is with probably.
With this arrow means is you'll you'll just stay next period one the arrows are one step transition probability transitions.
And the labels are the probabilities so you'll stay here.
You might go here.
You notice there's no there's no arrow like this.
That would be a different mark off chain.
There's nowhere like this if you want to get.
If you want to get to three to step third state.
You're going to have to go through the intermediate state and so on.
Okay.
So just moving ahead.
So you know just summarize what a mark off chain is going to be a.
It's going to be a pair.
It's going to be a stochastic matrix.
And an initial.
A marginal distribution over.
The time zero state.
It's the marginal distribution over the time zero state.
Okay.
So here's this is kind of a key.
This is going to be a key sentence.
So one way to study questions about mark off chains is just a simulator.
And big parts of statistics actually do this.
They take mark off chains and they simulate them to learn things.
Actually about the chain.
So.
This.
We're going to spend some time talking about this bullet point.
There's a lot in here to approximate the probability of an event e.
What you can do is you can run a simulation many times.
And then you count fractions.
Okay. So do you remember we spent some time talking about what this probability mean.
So what a frequent is thinks that what probability means is the.
Fraction.
That can be anticipated in a very large sample.
And that's being exploited right here.
Here's some advertisement.
There's.
We if you go to.
Quanty.
We've written python programs that.
That make it very easy for you to study and simulate mark off chains.
So what we're going to what this.
This.
So the quantity.
Content did to work for you there.
But it's actually mark off chains are so.
Fun and interesting to get your hands on it.
What this lecture does is it backs up and actually.
From scratch using numpy.
It's going to.
It's going to generate some.
It's going to show you how to simulate a mark off chain.
So.
So let's spend a little time talking about that.
And then in your time.
I think.
This is a great way to learn python and build your confidence is.
Do this to.
And do some examples.
So here's how to make your own.
The first thing we need.
The first thing we need is.
We have to have a mark off chain.
So.
What we call what I called.
Pys zero here we're going to call this.
Going to change no.
Going to call this.
Whatever that word is.
So a mark off chain is going to be a p.
So that's the time zero probability.
That's the time zero marginal.
And that's the transition matrix.
So if you give me.
Those two you define a mark off chain.
And then here's how one simulate.
Here's what I want.
Simulates.
Using random numbers at time t zero.
We're going to draw.
A random state.
From the marginal distribution at time zero.
And then every subsequent time period.
We're going to draw.
The new state.
From the transition probability matrix.
So this is the initial.
And this is transitions.
And that's how we're going to use it.
So.
You know, to make to make this go, we need one more thing.
We need a p a psi.
And we need a random number generator.
So.
And we're going to use.
We're going to use a.
Something from quantity.
So.
So this.
So code is actually describing how that's done.
And example would be.
Here's here's here's the language.
Here's the language.
This.
I think it's really good to slowly read Python code.
It's good for your character.
It's good for mind.
That's a line that says that generates a.
A distribution that I want.
So we talked about this earlier.
Like if I give you a probability distribution.
How can you generate a random draw from it?
Well, this is how quantity comes going to do it.
So I start with a probability distribution psi right here.
And then that's what I want.
I want a cumulative distribution function.
So what.
I'm now going to just that's just a.
A numpy command.
I'm going to compute the cumulative distribution.
And then what quantity kind of do is.
Quant quantity kind of random dot draw CDF of.
I'm going to draw from this CDF random draw and it tells me give me five numbers.
And my five numbers is going to give me well there.
I drew a.
Success success success failure.
So I drew.
Okay, so that's we're going to use that.
So we have our three things.
We have a p.
We have a psi and we have a random number generator.
And now we're all dressed up and ready to go.
So we're going to.
This quantity kind code in this little thing.
We're going to write us to casting matrix p.
We're going to need an initial state.
And we're going to take a sample size.
So.
What I want you to do is.
Study this on your own because now we're.
Quote in quote rolling our own.
We're writing.
Python function.
That's going to.
That's going to generate a.
A sample path.
Of length.
Well, you're going to make this up.
Because there's these key word arguments.
We're going to make this up.
We're going to input a p and we're going to input a.
An initial condition.
An initial distribution.
And then we're going to do a.
As.
A sample size.
So here we go.
So.
So here's our we here's how this works.
Just just an example would take this mark off chain.
Um.
Here's a claim.
That's what does probability mean again.
We're cycling back to that idea.
And this this is a claim.
A reminder and a claim that this is going to be verified.
Um.
So.
Well, we're going to verify very soon.
That's the claim.
What does probability mean?
That's a classic question.
Um.
So what we're going to do is we're going to use this code.
Create.
So X is going to be.
We're going to generate how many a hundred thousand.
You should try that on your machine.
There's our mark off chain.
We're going to try with from this initial distribution.
And.
And we're going to generate a very long chain.
And then the claim here in this lectures that.
The sample the sample mean is going to be.
The sample a mean for this for a very long sample is going to be around .25.
And notice when we.
Um.
We generated this and then we used numpy.
To.
To actually to actually compute the.
I mean and it it turns out to be very close to .25.
Now.
Let me make a claim.
It's going to make us somewhat clear.
Serious claim before I kind of pause this.
What we're talking about.
I claim.
That if you compute.
The.
Left.
I can.
Vectors.
Of this matrix that matrix left I can vector.
Associated I'll put a I'm going to take the left I can vector of that matrix associated.
With.
The unit.
I can value.
I'm so I'm claiming that this matrix.
As a unit I can value.
You could do this in exercise if you take the left I can vector of that.
And you normalize it.
Then.
You.
Will compute.
I'm going to say something called.
The.