Hello, this is Spencer Lyon and in this lecture we're going to continue talking about the
Lake Model of unemployment dynamics and we're going to seek to understand how we can
use the model and tie its parameters to US data so that we can have the data teach us
something about the models parameters.
Before we dive in on the Lake Model we want to remind ourselves of some of the higher level
concepts we've been working with.
In particular we want to review some of the standard notation and language that we're
using so that we can keep a perspective of how this particular example fits into the
larger framework that we've been building throughout this course.
So first we have the notion of a statistical model which is a joint probability density
F over some random variable some data Y and some parameters theta.
Now with this statistical model we might think about solving two distinct but related
problems.
The first problem is called the direct problem and the direct problem is to draw a random
example Y and notice here our notation we use the lower case little Y to mean a draw
from our model F and the upper case big Y to represent the data.
Now again the direct problem is to draw a sample Y from the statistical model represented
by F for some assumed or fixed value of the parameter vector theta.
On the other hand the inverse problem will be to take a set of data which we'll call Y
tilde and we're going to make an assumption or an assertion that this data was in fact
generated from the model F. We will then use this data and the assumption about it being
drawn from F and F's functional form and we'll use that combination in order to make some
inferences or to learn something about an unknown parameter vector theta.
But in slightly different terms the direct problem is to construct a simulation of our
model F for a given parameter vector theta. Other names for this simulated data set again
noted a little lower case Y might be artificial data or fake data.
The inverse problem is also called the parameter estimation problem. This name comes from
the fact that when we're solving the inverse problem we are taking some observed data,
assuming that it was generated from F and then trying to learn something about our estimate
values of our parameter vector theta. A third way to think about this is that the direct
problem takes parameters theta as inputs and then it generates artificial or fake data as outputs.
The inverse problem takes data, often real world data as its input, often we call this the
observations or the observed data and with these as an input it will then generate statements
or inferences about the parameters theta as the output. The inverse problem consumes data
and returns something about our parameters as an output. One key thread underlying both of
these model these problems are that they use the same statistical model F of a given data.
There are some tools that allow us to solve the direct problem which again relates to simulating
artificial data and these tools in fact turn out to be helpful when solving the inverse problem
or learning something about the parameter vector theta. We're going to be continuing in this
general framework of a statistical model the direct problem in the inverse problem as we talk
today about the lake model of unemployment that we've been working with and we want to make sure
that as we work through the materials in this lecture that you keep this overall framework in mind
and our goal today will be to use the lake model and its parameters and inferences we can make
about its parameters given real world data from the BLS and it will help us understand
the unemployment and employment rates over time and how they may change in various settings or in
various economic climates. This first code cell here will just import some of the tools we'll be using.
We're going to import pandas, numpy, and map plotlib. We'll just going to apply some style to our
figures and then we also import the built-in random library so that we can set the random seed.
And we do this just so that when we come back and we execute this code or this notebook in the
future we'll be able to see the same outputs and our work will be reproducible.
So let's review some facts that we've observed about the data. In particular we want to look at the
unemployment rate in the United States in the past two recessions. We obtained data from the
Bureau of Labor Statistics or BLS and as noted in previous lectures we saw a large shift in the
employment and unemployment numbers in the United States in the beginning of the year 2020.
And let's remind ourselves what these data look like. We have prepared a CSV file called BLS
Reset Recessions Data that will read into a data frame using pandas read CSV function.
We'll then construct a few extra columns. So we have as columns of this data frame
a column named Employed which represents the total number of persons
that were employed when the survey, when the underlying survey was given as well as the total number
of persons that were unemployed at the time the survey was administered. If we sum these two
up we'll call this the Labor Supply. Then with this Labor Supply in hand we're just going to
compute the fraction of workers that participated in the survey that were employed at the time
of the survey and then unemployed. So we'll go ahead we'll import the data, create these in
columns and we'll take a look at the first few rows. So the columns of note that we should
point out here there's a column called Recession. This takes on two values one is GR which is
short hand for the great recession. There's also another value in this column called COVID
which again represents the early 2020 months when there was a large shift in labor market dynamics
due to the COVID-19 pandemic. We then see the employed and unemployed columns talked about before
as well as our new columns, Labor Supply employed percent and unemployed percent over here on the right.
We'll talk about some of these other columns, EEE and UU and a little bit and the other thing to
keep in mind is there is this column called Months from and what this represents is it's always
an integer and it represents the number of months from the peak of unemployment associated with
the given recession. So this first row corresponds to the great recession and Months from has a value
of minus 35. So this would be 35 months prior to the peak unemployment observed during the
great recession. So this is about three years before the peak unemployment. We'll actually be able
to visualize this data here on the next page. So what we have here, the function and we'll go back
and look at it in a moment but this is the type of, this is the plot generated by our function.
So we see here we have two subvellers in our graph. The first subplot up at the top shows the
percent of employed workers given number of months before and after the the trial for the low point
in the labor market during the recession. So you'll see here that the blue line that lives up here
and then has the large spike downward represents the COVID era unemployment dynamics and the red line
that is more gradual represents the great recession era employment dynamics. This top subplot
would represent the share of persons that are employed and it's why access ranges from about 85
percent to about 96 percent. The bottoms of graph would just be exactly one minus the top one,
which is why you see kind of the mirror pattern down here on the bottom. It's almost as if it was
reflected about this space in between the two charts. Now let's look at the code that generated this
just so we have a sense of what it does. So what you can read the doc string and we encourage you
to take a look at this on your own time. But we'll talk through the high point right now. So this function
will consume a data frame and then what we will do is it will construct a 2 by 1 figure of
subplots and it will plot both the employed percent and unemployed percent. The employed percent
columns get put on the first subplot and the unemployed percent get put on the bottoms of flat.
Then what we do is we will group by the recession column of the data frame and we will plot this
group so this would contain only data for a single instance of that recession column,
or a single value of the recession column. And we'll plot on the horizontal axis the months from
column, which you see down here and then why is going to be either employed percent or unemployed
and then we do a little bit of work to kind of clean up the look for the chart and we return it.
And what this function will allow us to do is if we happen to have say three different
groups in the data frame of the recession column we would see three lines on each of these charts.
And we'll use this throughout the lecture today as we're going to add a third set of
rows to a data frame which will represent the model output and we'll see that here shortly.
So we just had a reminder and one thing actually let's go back to this
to one more look. So we noticed a couple patterns here first before the the low point of the current
COVID related unemployment. Things where I are fairly steady or fairly smooth there was roughly
4% unemployment and then very quickly within the matter of one period there is a sharp decline
in employment all the way down to about 85% and then a rather quick recovery or at least that's
what the data looks like up until the end of the data set. In contrast the great recession
looks quite a bit different. So the three years prior to the low point of employment during the
greater session did not see a steady value like we did in the COVID era but rather a slow decline
and slow loss of jobs that finally culminated right here at the worst point or the lowest point
of the employed percent and then a very slow and gradual ascension in the number of
in the percentage of employed workers representing a slow or gradual recovery.
Now throughout the lecture we will use the lake model to capture kind of both of these dynamics
but keep in mind that the great recession and the COVID era data from the BLS they show a very
different pattern from one another. Now that we've reminded ourselves with the data look like
let's remind ourselves what the model is that we've been working with. So the lake model in each
period has two parameters. First parameter we've called alpha and this is the probability of an
unemployed worker finding a job. We're going to refer to this as the job finding rate.
The second parameter is beta. This is the probability of an employed worker losing their job.
This is going to be called the job separation rate in today's lecture.
So these are the two parameters. This would be the container divector theta from our
description at the beginning of this lecture. There's also one state variable. We've been calling it S
and S is a two by one vector of percentages of unemployed and employed workers respectively.
So these are two numbers between zero and one that sum to one. One thing to point out is that if
the values of alpha and beta remain constant is not possible for our model to generate
sudden and large changes in the unemployment rate like those showcased in the COVID era
BLS data. Keep this in mind it's something we're going to try to address throughout our lecture today.
So let's take a quick look. We took some of the routines from a former lecture and we put them in a
standalone pipeline file called v1 employmentmodel.py. We're going to import these functions
under the alias emp and we're also going to keep numpy around as we'll be using that throughout our
code today. What we'll do is we'll first create a new Python class that we'll use throughout our
lesson today. And the purpose for this is that the class will allow us to keep track of the model
parameters that alpha and the beta. We'll also have routines for simulating a panel of workers
and it will help us combine the simulated data with the data from the BLS so that we can plot results
and compute statistics from our simulation. Now the Python class it looks quite long but most of the
lines are actually documentation and comments so they can be helpful as yourself studying after
this lecture's over. We'll review each of the functions each of the methods that make up the class
and it should be clear once we're finished or I walk through what the class does.
So here we go. The class is going to be called Lake Model Simulator. It's a knit method. This is
the method that we used to create a new instance or a new version of our simulator. It has just
two parameters. One is called N and this will just represent the number of individuals that we would
like to include in our simulated data. The second parameter here is called S0. This will
represent the initial or starting steady state or starting state value for beginning our simulations.
Here we've gone ahead and we've set default values for both of these parameters. By default,
our simulator will simulate 5,000 workers at every time step and it will set the initial state
equal to about 2.3% unemployment and then about 97.6% unemployment.
Sorry, 97.6% employment. We'll go ahead and all the admit method does in this case is it just
stores these values for later. We then have a block of code right here that defines what's called
a property. So these parameters here, the N as well as the underscore S0, our call of properties.
In our case, we wanted to put a little bit more structure around how the property S0 without the
leading underscore would work. By default, when we try to get S0, meaning when we try to type
the lakemodel dot S underscore zero, what's going to happen is it's going to actually run this
function and all we're going to be doing is returning the current value of underscore S0.
This is the same as the behavior we would get from here from just using,
for if we are trying to access N. So we're not really leveraging the fact that this is a property
with custom behavior. The custom behavior comes in the second half of the property, which is
called the set method or the setter. Now the set method, it needs to take in a new proposal for
the initial state. And the reason we're defining this as a custom property is because we want
to make sure that whatever anybody passes in is an array that has two values and we want to also
assert that they sum to one. This just allows us to make sure that whatever the user of our class
wants to change the starting state before a new simulation, they set it properly by having a
two element vector that sums to one. If those two both paths, we will then just set this
underscore S0 property to the array that was passed in and then whenever somebody uses LM dot S0,
this will be returned to them via our get function above. So once we have these defined,
we just need to connect them using the special property function built into Python. So this code
right here allows us to have custom behavior for setting the S0 property. If I didn't have a
two element array or it didn't sum to one, this attempt to set a new value for S0 would be rejected.
This is just a showcase. One of the features that Python affords us to make sure that we don't
have an inconsistent version of our model. Okay, the next method will be to combine with the data
from the BLS. So this takes two parameters. One, we've called DFSM, which is short for the data frame
that we obtain via simulation. And then the second one is called DFBLS. We've set a default value for
this to the DFBLS. We imported above from the CSV file and used to construct our plots.
Now this, the main part of this function is just to concatenate these two and stack them on
top of each other. However, there's one thing we need to do, which is right here. We need to adjust
the month from column to begin at negative 35. So by default, our simulation routines will set the
lowest value of the month from column to zero. It will just simulate from time zero, forward.
And in order for everything to line up properly with the data obtained from the BLS and how we've
ordered it, we need to subtract 35 so that our simulation also begins at negative 35.
So once we've done that, we'll just stack them together and then return.
Next, we have a method called simulate panel. So here, this is going to be kind of a
wrapper function around the simulate employment cross section method that we saw in our last
lecture together. Our last lecture on the lake model. The two parameters that are consumed by this
method are alpha and beta. These are going to be arrays that contain the value of alpha and beta
for every time step of the simulation. So they will have lake the T and they will be passed
into the simulate method from the employment file. We're going to then pass in the S0 that's
part of the class right now as the initial state as well as the number of individuals that's also
a property of our class. This will be an N by T array filled with entirely the number 0 and 1.
We're 0 indicates a worker being unemployed in that period and a 1 indicates a worker being employed.
Well then extract the shape of the number of columns which are present this number T so that we can
use it again now below. Then once we have all these workers, we'll simply sum
over all the N in each period to get a total number of workers that were employed.
Finally the last thing this does is it puts it in a data frame and this data frame will have four
columns. The first is month from and as mentioned before this will just start at 0 and increment
by 1 in each row and it will end at T minus 1. So it has T elements.
Then we have a column called employed percent and importantly this is the same column name
that showed up in the BLS data frame from above and this will be the number of employees. There's
the number of workers that were employed every period which we computed above
divided by the total number of employees in our panel. There's a total number of workers in our
panel and finally we'll also compute the unemployed percent which is going to be 1 minus that
and we will set the recession column to the constant model so that when we use our plotting
routine to find a above we will have a legend entry that reads model. This will be kind of the
workhorse of our our work today and this solves the direct problem. So notice that as an input
to this function or this method we receive parameters. This is this alpha and beta would be like
the the parameter vector theta that we spoke about at the beginning and the output of this method
is a simulation from the model f. The model f is encapsulated in how we use the parameters
alpha and beta in order to produce a simulation of the data. So our core simulation routine here
allows us to solve the direct problem. We then have one more helper method in this class where
we are labeling an easy routine for simulating a panel of workers where alpha and beta are fixed
at their time zero values and so all we'll do here is we'll construct a vector of alpha
which will be the constant alpha zero of vector of beta which is the constant beta zero
and we'll use the function or the method to find above to run a simulation and return a data frame.
So we'll evaluate the cell to define our function and we'll be ready to start using that here shortly.
Okay we're now ready to put our new class and its simulation routines to work. So to begin we will
first simulate a a quote normal time or non-recession version of the data and we will refer to these
parameters as alpha and beta but with a bar over it. So alpha bar is 0.37 which represents a
job finding rate for the unemployed of about 37%. Meanwhile the normal time or steady state version
of the beta parameter or the job separation rate is about 1%. And again we're going to refer to
these parameters with the bar over them as the steady state parameters and we'll talk soon about
why we we choose this term steady state and we'll remind you that these values were computed using
data from the CPS in an earlier lecture. If you remember our simulation routine also required that we
pass a value for the initial state of employed and unemployed workers will refer to this as
S bar and we'll note that it has about 2.37% of unemployed and about 97.6% of workers that were employed.
Again these were also previously estimated using the CPS data. So we'll define these three
constants right here and then in the next cell we will use them to simulate we use them with our
simulator to produce a chart that includes the data from the BLS as well as our simulated data.
So these blue and red lines are the same that we saw before. They represent the COVID era in blue
and the great recession era in red. But now we have a new yellow line that represents kind of the
the model generated data using the steady state parameters. So notice that we passed in an unemployment
rate, a starting unemployment rate of about 2.3% which is right here in the yellow line and because
we were in steady state the model stayed roughly at that place. We didn't see large we didn't see
gradual decline in employment or increase and we didn't see a large spike as we do in these other
two lines. This is one of the reasons we call the set of parameters the steady state parameters
because it's a a place of aggregate rest for the model. So visually we can see that this steady
state version of the model. It doesn't match features of either recession. So the COVID recession had that
really sharp drop in employment which wasn't replicated in the steady state model simulation.
And again the great recession data set had that gradual decline and then after the
trough was reached a gradual increase in employment which again was inconsistent with the model being
very constant and flat over time. Our goal in the rest of our lecture today will be to
discover deviations from the model where we set alpha equal to alpha bar for our periods and beta
equal to beta bar for our periods. There will have a lake model to do a better job of
describing times of stress in the US labor market. In order to understand the effectiveness of our
modeling decisions we need to talk about the concept of a last function. So a last function is a
deterministic mathematical function that measures the difference between a model's output and its target.
The last function is a key component to any statistical optimization routine or practice and it is heavily
used in machine learning in order to evaluate the goodness of fit of a particular model.
In today's lecture we're going to be using a very common last function called the mean squared
error last function or written MSE for short. It's defined as follows given a sequence of targets
and model outputs y and y hat. The MSE is defined as the average 1 over n of summing up the difference
between the target and the model output squared. So we'll compute the residual or the loss for
each observation. We'll square that loss and then we'll compute the average of all those squared
losses. That's what is meant by the average or mean squared error. This is where it gets its name.
For the current exercise that we're undergoing the model output will be the time series of the
percentage of workers that are employed. The target will be the corresponding time series
from the BLS and we will compute the last function independently for both the great recession
error data as well as the COVID error data. We've defined here a function that takes in a
data frame that has the same shape and features as the data frame we're plotting and it will compute
the MSE between the model and the great recession error data and the model and the COVID error data.
So to do this we use some of our reshaping tools we've learned. First we construct a pivot table
by setting the index to be the months from column. Then across the columns we're going to have
different values of recession. In this case we'll have GR for great recession as a column. COVID will be
another column and model will be another column. The values that are referred to by this row and
column label will just come from the employee percent column of the input data frame.
We're going to multiply each of these by 100 to put them in percentage units and this is actually
we'll just make the MSE bigger and a little easier to compare across models because we won't be dealing
with very small numbers. Once we have this pivot table computing the MSE looks very similar to
its formulaic representation. So what we'll do is for each row or each value of months from
we will compute the difference between the model level of employed percentage and the great
recession level of employed percentage and then we'll square that difference.
Once we've done this for each row we'll have a pandas series after this code is evaluated
and then we'll just compute the mean or the average of each of these squared error terms.
We'll repeat this for both the great recession column and the COVID column.
And the reason we used a pivot table there were two reasons one by setting the index two months from
we're allowing pandas to align the operations here where we do model minus great recession and
pandas will align the observations to make sure that we're subtracting a month from of 10
in the model to a month from of 10 in the great recession.
And the second reason was so that we could have these three versions of our data,
great recession, model and COVID each becomes so they're easy to operate.
Once we do that we can define the function and use it to evaluate the efficacy of our steady state.
And just kind of keep these numbers in mind as we move forward. So the the mean squared error,
the average squared deviation of our steady state model for our good recession data
ended up being about 29%. Or value 29%age points. Remember that was the units we chose.
So the mean squared error was about 29 and for the COVID data it was about 12.
So just kind of keep these numbers in the back your head as these are going to be our benchmark
for evaluating one model versus another one.
And in particular the use of a loss function allows us to be precise about what we mean when we say
a model is better or has improved upon a different model.
It allows us to move from a qualitative notion of how good a model fits the data to a very
quantitative version. So for example instead of saying model 2 appears to do better than model 1
that matching the spike in the COVID error unemployment. We could say that the MSC COVID from model 2
is 5.1 relative to the value of 11.5 from model 1. So we've moved from a qualitative statement here
to a quantitative numerical statement down below. And this will make it easier to have
interpretable results that are completely objective.
We'll now begin putting in a different models on the table and seeing what they can help us learn
about unemployment data in the United States. So let's first consider the hypothesis that the spike
observed in the COVID-19 era unemployment data was only due to a redistribution of workers in the
initial period. But it didn't actually change the job creation or separation rates.
In terms of our model parameters, this hypothesis would mean that alpha t is equal to its steady
state value alpha bar for alt t. And similarly beta t is always equal to its steady state value of beta bar.
This is what we meant by the hypothesis saying that the job creation and job separation rates
were not changed. Then we'll say that we can begin our simulation at time t equals 0 at the steady state
or S bar. Then we will say that s t is the shocked value of s. We'll talk about this soon
where the subscript t or the date is just the date of the shock. Then for all tau greater than t,
the value of the state in period tau will just be dictated by the lake model and the parameters
alpha and beta. So we'll be using again in order to compute what the state is in period's
greater than t will be using our solution to the direct problem by fixing the parameters alpha and beta
and simulating our model forward to obtain the state in periods after the shock.
We'll make one note here that for any tau sufficiently greater than t,
you will have that the state in period tau is going to be approximately equal to the steady state state
S bar. This is actually what is meant by a steady state. It is a place of rest according to the
dynamics of the model. If the model is at the steady state today and the parameters remain at
their steady state values, the model will be at the parameter to steady state again in the next period.
We actually have all the tools we need to inspect this hypothesis visually and we'll
lay out a few steps for how we'll do it. The first step to visually inspect this hypothesis
would be to set the initial state equal to the steady state value. Then we will fix the parameters
alpha and beta at their steady state values for all time periods.
Now because we want to inspect visually and compare against the data from the BLS,
we know how long we need to simulate before the shock. So what we'll do is starting from the steady
state and keeping parameters fixed, we'll simulate for 35 periods. This would be from period
minus 35 to minus 1 inclusive. Then at time t equals zero, we will set the state.
By hand, we'll reach into the model and we'll reshuffle our workers so that there are 14% of
our workers will now be unemployed and then the balance or 86% will be employed.
This is approximately the value that was observed in the spring of 2020 because of COVID-19.
Then we can from that point forward simulate for the other 36 periods that
correspond to the length of the BLS time series and finally we'll stitch together these two
halves of the simulation, the pre-shock half and the post-shock half.
Should notice that this is very similar to what we did when we'd simulated the steady state.
We're the only differences here at step four at period zero. We the model, we reach our hand
into the model and we cut some of the employed worker jobs, we separate them from their jobs
and move them into the unemployed bucket. And that's it and then we let the model continue
to apply its dynamics going forward using the direct problem and our solution to it and we obtain
our simulation. So in code we follow these same steps. Here we make sure that the initial state is S bar
and we simulate for the first 35 periods from zero to 34.
Then we will need to apply the shock, this is step four. And the way we do this is we will set
the S0 parameter of our Lake model equal to the shock value which we pass in as an argument here.
And the reason we're setting the says S0 equal to ST is because we're effectively starting
a brand new simulation where the shock value will become the initial state for the simulation
from this point on. We'll then go ahead and simulate the second half. We'll need to make sure
that we adjust the months from column to make sure that it picks up exactly where this data
frame before left off. And then we'll just concatenate the two and stick them together. And finally
we combine them with the BLS data so that we're ready to plot or compute the MSC straight away.
Sure, our solution is to simulate in two halves. We first simulate from the steady state
without changing anything. We then shock the state, simulate afterwards and stitch the output together.
We'll go ahead and we'll do that and we'll call the value DF shock and we'll plot the results
alongside the model from the data. And we'll see here that we do have a steady state up at the top
all the way until period T-1. Then at period zero we immediately drop down to about the value of
that COVID recession which would be 86% of the workers employed. And then the model dynamics kick in
and as the job finding rate is at a steady state value of 37%. The number of the percent of
workers employed goes up up but it continues to climb until it reaches a steady state value and then
stays roughly constant after that. So because the job finding rate is high at 37% and the job
separation rate is low at 1%. This level of only 86% of them workers being employed is not sustainable
by those model parameters and the number of employed workers are the percentage of employed
workers continues to climb until it reaches its steady state value again. So one thing to point out here
is that the dynamics before the shock and even up into it were fairly similar for the COVID era
and the model. The model had a slightly higher stable or steady state unemployment or shy employment
numbers but the pattern of being consistent and flat up until a large spike is the same across both.
What is different however though is that the model holding that job finding and job separation rate
constant causes a much quicker recovery, a quicker increase in the percentage of workers employed
in the model than we see in the data. The regates to be a gap in the between these two lines
that grows wider as we move forward in time. This is even more pronounced when we consider how quickly
the model is able to recover relative to the great recession. So here it looks like the difference between
about 97% and 86. If we split it right down the middle would be somewhere around here and it
looks like it's getting there after just one or two periods. Contrast this with what happens in the
great recession where if we want to go from say 95 to 90 you want to go back to 92 and a half
this doesn't happen until almost 35 months after the the low point in employment from the great recession.
So this recovery from the great recession was much slower than our model would be predicting.
Let's go ahead and evaluate the last function. We'll see here that the MSC for the great recession
didn't move very much before with the original model that didn't have the spike it was between 25
and 30 and it still is. However the MSC for the COVID era, what data has fallen significantly.
This should be expected because when we reached in as the modeler and shifted the balance of
employment and unemployment to artificially mimic this spike we should see that the model does a
bit better because for these few periods were much closer to the blue line then we would have been
had we stayed up here in the steady state. So the fact that the MSC fell is entirely a feature
generated kind of in these 10 periods where we go from zero to when we've recovered which is at about
the MSC in this simulation is going to be smaller than it would have been had we stayed up here
the entire time and that shows up right here with this number being about four instead of something close to 10 or 12.
From the analysis we just completed. We've learned that even when we artificially adjust or shock
the state at time t equals zero to match the great recession the steady state values of our job
finding in separation rates are inconsistent with the market dynamics during the COVID era recession.
This was manifest in our model featuring a faster recovery than the actual COVID era data from the
BLS. As we think about this we would realize that our assumption that alpha and beta remain constant
is likely too strong in addition to a redistribution of our workers between employment and unemployment
there may also have been a shift in the job separation and finding rates during this period.
We'll explore that hypothesis here in what we'll call model two.
So we're going to relax the assumption that alpha and beta are always fixed at their steady
state values but we're going to do so in a very disciplined and specific way.
And here's how we're perceived. We're going to assume that before the time t equals zero
shock occurs alpha and beta with the subscript t are going to be fixed and held at their steady state values.
Then we're going to continue to assume that the state s t immediately jumps to the
spiked COVID levels so far this is the same as what we did in the previous model.
Now we're also going to assume that starting at times zero and continuing temporarily for
n a finite number of periods alpha and beta will move to new values alpha hat and beta hat.
Once those n periods are over alpha and beta will return to their steady state values of alpha
bar and beta bar. Mathematically these assumptions are expressed as follows.
Alpha sub t is going to be equal to alpha hat only when t is between zero and n.
In all other periods including t less than zero and t greater than n,
alpha will be equal to alpha bar. The same holds for beta. We're going to have beta hat
only between zero and n and beta bar in all other periods.
We will define a function that can do this for us. So here this function again takes our
lake model simulator as an argument and then it needs to know the shocked values of alpha hat
beta hat as well as how long to hold them n and it needs to know where to adjust the state at
times zero. So once we take as an input these parameters our solution to the direct problem
described above is as follows. Our before t equals zero code remains exactly the same and even
up until t equals zero our movement of the state directly to the shocked value is going to mimic
what we saw in the previous direct model for model one. What changes is what happens starting at t equals
zero. So we're going to construct a vector of alpha which represent alpha sub t. We're going to have
him have length 35 and we're going to start out sitting all of them equal to alpha bar.
Then the first n values of this vector are going to be adjusted so that it equals alpha hat
in those periods. This is how we apply this mathematical function that was part of our model up above.
This is our direct model solution or direct problem solution to this modeling feature we
described up here. We repeat the same thing for the beta parameter. We'll use our lake model
simulate panel routine that can accept this vector of alpha's and datas. As we did before we have to
adjust the months from in the second half of our panel to account for the fact that we've already
simulated from periods by 34 up until zero and then we stitch the two together combine with the
BLS data and return. So this code is going to be the same as what we saw before. We'll evaluate this
cell and we will test it out. So we're going to go ahead and put on our thinking caps and
recognize that in order to slow down the recovery of our model we may need to decrease the job
finding rate and that would mean moving it from zero point three seven is something smaller.
Here we're just going to pick the values 0.28. We have no reason to believe that this is any better or
worse than another value smaller than 0.37. We're just testing out one possible model which
includes setting alpha hat to 0.28. Another thing that might slow down the recovery would be if
the job separation rate rises. It's steady state value is at 1% and we'll just move it up to 5%
and see what happens. And then we'll suppose or pause it at this last for three periods.
We'll go ahead and we'll use our new simulation routine or our new solution to the direct problem.
With the values of alpha hat at 0.28, beta hat at 0.05 that are held there for three periods
and then we'll plot it and compute the MSC. So we see here visually that the model went down
to the same value but then it fell a little too far and it ended up reaching about the same place
as the the COVID data about five months after the the low point unemployment and then it continued
its recovery. But in this region from 0 to about five the model actually underestimated the recovery
and employment. This was better than the previous model if you remember the previous model moved
up in this region and quickly recovered and visually we can kind of see that that's better
but precisely and numerically we can see that it's better because our MSC for the COVID
era data went down from about four or four and a half to now it's about two and a half.
So we've made an improvement in the mean squared error between the yellow line representing our
model and the blue line representing the COVID era data. So these initial test values as we just
noticed did improve the MSC but we didn't have any reason to believe that the values we picked
were going to be the optimal or best values. There are infinite numbers of configurations of
alpha hat, beta hat and end we could have tried or infinite number of other models we could have used.
And so what we're going to do next is we're going to assume the role of the visual
econometrition and hard goals will be to look at these graphs and graphs and the MSC
to try to manually adjust alpha hat, beta hat and end to improve upon this MSC of 2.6.
So we're going to utilize the ipy widgets library to create an interactive version of our chart.
So here we see that we're going to wrap the simulate plot and MSC steps in a function
and then we're going to use the intractor team and say how we'd like
alpha hat to be manipulated, beta hat to be manipulated and then a starting value for end.
And what this did was it returned our MSC like we had before and we see that we're still near
that value of 2.6. Any deviation from exactly 2.6 is because there is randomness in the simulation.
So we shouldn't expect to get the same value every time. It'll be slightly different each time we
run it. So we have the MSC we have the plot but now we also have these three little widgets
here that allow us to be the visual econometrition. If we slide this bottom widget,
this will allow us to change the value of n or change the stickiness of the alpha hat and beta hat
parameters. And you'll see here as we make n quite large but is doing to our plot here
is it's making this region where the model has an output employment percentage of about 0.85.
It's making that longer and longer. So we see here that n is currently at a value of 9,
which corresponds visually to going from 0 to 9 here and it has this whole region.
Then as soon as the model parameters are set back to their steady state value,
we see this very sharp and quick or very smooth and quick recovery back to the steady state.
So let's set this back to something a little more moderate. Maybe three. And let's see what happens
if we play with the job finding rate alpha hat. As we make this bigger, so we would like to make
our recovery a bit faster than it currently is. We'd like to make sure that we're able to move
up and track this blue line better. So if we're going to change alpha hat, the job finding rate
would need to make it bigger. So it would make it bigger and bigger and bigger and it looks like this
current value of 42 percent would match the data pretty well. So if there was some way that we could raise the
job finding rate from the steady state value of about 37 percent to about 42 percent, that might help
the model match closely the data obtained from the BLS in the covid error.
Now if we think that this is probably not what's happening during this time period that there's
probably unlikely that more unemployed workers are finding work, this may not be what we want to do.
We might not want to be increasing the parameter alpha hat because that's inconsistent with our
beliefs about what's happening in the economy. In addition to looking at this just raw data of
the percentage of workers employed and unemployed, we could kind of use some of our other knowledge about
the total claims of workers claiming unemployment rising to maybe discount or discard the hypothesis
that the job finding rate is increasing to make this match. So what we'll do is we'll go and we'll
make this a little bit smaller. In fact it's probably more likely that the job finding rate has
fallen from a steady state value and we'll leave it here at something smaller than the 37 percent
in steady state. Now what's probably true is that the relative to the steady state value of 0.01 which
saw this two eager recovery from the model. We might believe that the job separation rate has increased.
So let's go ahead and increase it from 1 percent to 2 percent and we'll see here that we're very
closely matching the data and only at this kind of period three here do we see that it starts to take
off a little too fast. So let's go ahead and leave these values at 25 percent and 2 percent
and move up N1 more and now we see here that if we allow these adjusted parameters to
persist for four periods we're very closely the model's very closely tracking the COVID
era data. So let's summarize what we did. We first started experimenting and understanding with
what a change in N did and what it did is it delayed the rapid but smooth increase from
whatever value of employment percentage was currently held back to the steady state. As we made
N very large this value lengthened the duration over here until we see the rapid increase to the steady
state. If we make N very small then the if we again 0 so there is no alpha-hatter beta-hat
then we see an immediate sharp or immediate quick increase back to the steady state.
Then we thought about what if we only move alpha-hat what if we only change the job finding rate.
We found that in order to match the dynamics observed in the COVID era data we would need to
have a job finding rate that was higher than the steady state job finding rate. This was
inconsistent with our beliefs as observant economists that more unemployed workers were finding
our beliefs were that there were more people being unemployed and it was harder for them to find
jobs. So trying to sort of have an increase in this job finding rate was inconsistent with that.
So we then said well what if we move the job finding rate somewhere below the steady state?
How much would we need to then increase the job separation rate to have the model match the
COVID era data and that led us to increase the job separation rate from 1% to 2%.
And this exercise that we just performed is kind of the cracks of doing computational social
science. It included three main components. One was the data. That was this blue line
that was the actual or real world data that we were trying to match and we were trying to have
our model track. The second main component was the statistical model. It was the hypothesis
that the model parameters alpha and beta shifted from their steady state values to alpha-hat
for finite number of periods. We had a way to toggle these parameters and adjust them
and that led to different statistical models that we had a direct solution to. A direct problem solution
to and we were able to produce these simulations. So feature number one was the data.
Feature number two was the model and then feature number three was our prior beliefs about which
levels of parameters are plausible and that helped us applying these prior beliefs helped us arrive
a set of parameters that both match the data and were consistent with our beliefs.
Had we not imposed that we may well have stopped when we found that alpha-hat of 45%.
But our belief said that that was inconsistent with what we knew and observed about the world.
Even though it was outside the model, there's nothing in our model about
individuals claiming unemployment or businesses closing down. The fact that we knew those things were happening
formed our prior beliefs and that led us to change the set of parameters we were willing to
consider. Those three components data, model and prior beliefs are at the heart of a lot of
computational social science and the heart of a lot of what we will be doing as we move forward
in this lecture. In this lecture in this course.
Okay, so we're going to summarize these three values. We had 25% job finding rate, a 2% job
separation rate and that these were last for four periods after that initial shock to the state of
the workers. When we did that, the MSC fell from about 2.4 to about 1.7.