Let's now talk about labor statistics.
By labor statistics, what we mean is the data that's used to measure and quantify the
health of labor markets.
So in the United States, one of the main sources for labor statistics is a survey known
as the current population survey.
And the survey has been in one version or another, been administered since the late 1930s.
But it collects data on kind of demographic and economic characteristics of individuals
and households.
The data it collected is administered.
So the survey is administered to roughly 60,000 households per month.
And rather miraculously they achieve an average response rate of nearly 90%.
Because there's about 60,000 households per month.
This means that they have a relatively good sample for geography such as state and metropolitan
statistical area.
But maybe this data isn't particularly accurate for geographic level like counties.
So one of the strengths of the CPS is its inherent panel nature.
Let's talk about why that's helpful.
So if we have kind of January, February, March, April, May, June, July, August, September, October, November,
December.
So here's the 12 months of the year.
So in the CPS, once you're selected, you're interviewed for four consecutive months.
And then you're interviewed for four consecutive months, again, eight months later.
So let's work through an example.
So imagine this is the year 2020.
And you begin being interviewed by the CPS in February.
Then you're interviewed in February, March, April, and May of 2020.
And then you wait eight months.
So not interviewed in June, not interviewed in July.
August, September, October, November, December.
And then we come into 2021 January.
So you've been out of the sample for eight months now.
And you begin being interviewed again in February, 2021, 2021.
So then you're interviewed again, February, March, April, and May.
So one of the strengths is that this results in you being interviewed during the same
set of months in two different years.
And additionally, because of this, you can track someone for consecutive months.
So you could see whether someone in March had lost a job that they currently, that they had
had in February or how their income might have changed, et cetera.
So this panel nature makes the CPS really helpful for asking lots of different labor market
questions.
So what types of things are asked?
The CPS collects information on demographics and labor status mostly.
So they'll ask you things like, how many people live in the household?
What are the sex age and race of these different people?
And what's the relationship between each set of people?
So this tells you things like our grandparents living in the house with their children
and their grandchildren.
It tells you whether other people in the house are deep in the head of the household
or whether they're children, et cetera.
It also collects information on whether you're working, whether you're working full-time
or part-time.
It gets an estimate of your hourly pay and how many hours you work.
They ask about whether you're looking for work, how you're looking for work, whether you're
retired, or whether you have any other disabilities.
And they ask lots of other things.
You can actually find their exact questionnaires online at the link in this notebook.
So who uses the CPS?
Well, the truth is, lots of people do.
The one we're going to be talking about mostly today is the Bureau of Labor Statistics.
And they issue a jobs report once a month based on the numbers collected by the current
population survey.
Additionally, because this data is open, researchers, anyone can access the micro data
behind the CPS, so you could collect these surveys and track these people on your own.
And actually, additionally, there's lots of private companies that use this information
for their own decision making.
Okay, so the next thing we're going to do is we're going to talk about some of the
common terms used in labor statistics.
So employed means an individual who did any work at all as a paid employee, whether
if they worked in their own business, worked on their own farm, or if they worked 15 or
more hours as unpaid workers in a family member's business.
And then part time is an individual who usually works less than 35 hours per week.
A full time individual is someone who usually works 35 or more hours per week.
And both of these definitions are defined across all jobs.
So if someone had what they considered two part time jobs, they were 20 hours a week each,
they would be considered a full time worker.
Unemployed means an individual who is not employed and was available to work and made an
active effort to find employment during the four week period, ending with the survey
reference week.
The labor force is the sum of the employed and unemployed individuals.
The unemployment rate is the number of unemployed people as a percentage of the labor
force.
And those not in the labor force are individuals aged 16 and older who were neither employed
nor unemployed.
And you can find more detail about each of these definitions in the BLS documentation.
So the last thing we're going to talk about are kind of definitionally that is going
to be things will call the transition rates.
And so these are key statistics that people use to analyze how the labor economy is
churning for lack of a better word.
So there's four different rates that we'll talk about.
There's the E to E rate, which is the fraction of people who are employed during the
current month and in the last month, E to E are the people who are the people who
are the people who transition from employed to unemployed, the E which is the people who
transition from the unemployed to the employed and the E to E which is the fraction
of people who are unemployed and continue to be unemployed.
And if we hold the labor force constant, what we get is that E E plus E U plus U E plus
U is equal to one.
And you can add additional states.
So for example, we could have an E N rate, which would be the number of people who fraction
of people who are employed previously and transitioned into not in the labor force.
There's something like that, but we're just going to focus on these four.
And I think this raises a natural question in kind of there's two ways to increase unemployment.
You could either see a decrease in what we'll call kind of the job finding rate, which
is the transition rate from unemployed to employed, or an increase in the firing rate,
and in the separation rate, I guess we'll call it, which is an increase in the rate of
employed to unemployed.
And so kind of in the back of your mind as we work through today's lecture and next week's
lecture, we want you to be thinking about which of these channels will have a larger effect
on unemployment levels.
And we'll ask you to do this formally next class.
So the question we're going to ask today with the data that we download is going to be
how changes in the transition rates changed between changed during two periods of economic
turbulence in the United States.
So we're going to analyze the great recession and the current pandemic to explore how these
different rates changed.
In particular, we saw large increases unemployment in unemployment, and we're going to
see what happened to the U.E. and the U.E. rates during these two times of economic turbulence.
So we'll do that at the end of class.