Hi everyone, we're going to start today's lecture by introducing a new data set.
This data set is from a company called Instacart.
Instacart is an online grocery retailer that sells and delivers grocery products.
The data that we'll use today comes from a subset of their data that they open sourced,
which includes 3 million different Instacart orders and contains data on which
particular items were ordered and which customer made each particular order.
As usual, we're going to import the package we need.
For this lecture, it will just be pandas because we're only working with a little bit
of data.
So this data set was initially released as a part of a Kaggle competition.
Instacart described this data set in the competition description saying the following.
The data set for this competition is a relational set of files.
You should remember this term.
We're going to come back to talking about this in the next video.
Describing customers orders over time.
The goal of the competition is to predict which products will be in a user's next order.
The data set is anonymized and contains a sample of over 3 million grocery orders from
more than 200,000 Instacart users.
For each user, we provide between 4 and 100 of their orders with the sequence of products
perched just in each order.
We also provide the weak and hour of day the order was placed and a relative measure of
time between orders.
For more information, see the blog post accompanying its public release.
So we've linked to this blog post and we're also adding a citation that they ask that
if we use this data source that we appropriately cite them.
Now let's start diving into the data and seeing what's contained.
The first file that they distribute as part of this data set is one called Isles.csv.
This file just contains some meta information about something they refer to as Isles.
They have an Isle ID which is just an integer and an Isle which is a string named describing
the integer.
For example, Isle ID 1 corresponds to prepared soups and salads.
Isle ID 4 corresponds to instant foods.
As we could see, Isle ID 131 is dry pasta 132 is beauty.
In addition to reading the data set in, we've gone ahead and we've saved it to a parquet file.
That's because some of these data sets that they're going to include are quite large.
So we're going to read in their raw CSV files, but then we're going to write out parquet
files to be able to load them more quickly.
The next data set we're going to look at is one called Department.
So department.csv is going to look a lot like Isles CSV and that it's going to contain
a department identifier which is called department ID and a string name for department
that describes which department we're working with.
So if we load this data, we see that department ID 1 corresponds with the frozen department.
Department ID 4 corresponds with produce and we could see there's only about 20 departments.
So we have 17 households and 18 corresponds to babies.
Next we come to the products.csv file.
This file contains metadata about each of the products and this has more than two columns.
Like the last two data sources.
So the first element is a product ID and this is going to be an identifier for the product
that was purchased.
There's going to be a product name which will be a string name that describes the product
that we're working with and then there's going to be an ILID and a department ID.
At the beginning, in the introduction that Instacart wrote for the Caggle competition,
they said that this was a relational data set.
And what they meant by relational is that each of the sub data sets.
So in this case, products.csv refers to other data sets that are bundled together.
In this case, we are referencing the IL and the department from the products.csv folder.
We can go ahead and load this just like the others.
And we see some examples of products.
So product ID 1 is chocolate sandwich cookies.
And that is found in ILID 61, which is in department 19.
Green chili anytime sauce is product ID 5, which is found in ILID 5, department ID 13.
So we might be interested in, for example, determining which ILs.
So let's group by ILID.count.
So all this is going to do is we're going to use the Pandas group by that we learned earlier in the course
to group by each of the IL IDs.
We're going to select the product name column and we're just going to count how many
non-missing values this takes.
So what we see and let's go ahead and
describe.
So the IL with the lowest number of items would be 12 items.
The IL with the most items has 1,258.
I'm actually a little bit curious about that sort of values, sending equals false.
And then we can again, we can merge IL.
That is set index dot merge IL on equals IL ID.
How equals left.
So the IL with the most, the most products in the IL is the IL called
missing.
So the IL that does not have anything followed closely by candy chocolate and ice cream ice.
I don't know what other kind of ice cream there is, but ice cream ice is the IL.
Let's go ahead and clean this up a little bit.
So it's not quite as ugly.
There we go.
That's a little more readable.
We may also be interested in which departments have the most products.
So again, we're now going to run the same code, but we're going to group by the different department
IDs.
And there's a much fewer departments than ILs.
So we should see more items per group.
We're going to again select the products name and count how many observations there were,
we're then going to sort these values, reset the index and we're going to merge now with
department on department ID.
And let's go ahead and run this.
So we'll see that the department with the most products is department 11, which was personal care
with 6,500 products.
I'm closely followed by the snacks department with 6,264 different products.
And I suspect that each IL corresponds to this is an open question.
I haven't actually answered this.
But I suspect each IL corresponds to a single department, but we can test this by grouping by both ILID
and department ID, selecting the product name counting, sorting the values.
Again, we're going to reset the index to move ILID and department ID into the columns.
And then we're going to merge on the IL and department data frames on their corresponding
identifiers.
And it looks like, oh, maybe I was wrong.
Let's go ahead and sort by the IL ID and the department ID.
And so what we see is IL1 has IC.
So it looks like each IL only has corresponds to a single department, but that there can be multiple ILs
per department. So for example, IL132 maps to department 11 as does department 133.
And that seems to hold true in a larger subset of the data.
So multiple ILs can map two way single department, but each IL only corresponds to a single
department. So in this case grouping by IL and department gives us the same
product accounts as grouping by IL would have.
Okay, well, we learned something. So let's keep exploring our data.
So the next file is exciting. So this is going to be the orders.csv file.
It's going to contain meta information about each of the three million orders that are
covered in the data set. The columns in the data set are order ID, which is a unique identifier for each order
user ID, which is a unique identifier for each consumer that made one of the three million orders.
So there's going to be three about three million different order IDs, but only two million
different user IDs or 200,000 rather 200,000 unique consumer IDs.
And then there's going to be an aval set. This is just a classifier that
Instacart used. They wanted this data to be used in a machine learning context. And so
they classified these orders into a prior order, a training order and a test order.
Then we're not going to use the aval set. Order number is going to be
which the order in which the individual made the given orders. So for example, we could see
the following. We could see order ID one made by user one.
Then we're not going to talk about a valset. And this might have been order one.
We could have seen a new order, which had order ID one or two,
made by consumer two. And this would have been their first order.
Then we could have seen an order ID three followed by perhaps order ID three was made by user one.
Then this would have been order number two made by user one. So this is user one's second order.
And we're going to track the order in which the orders were made.
There's going to be an order day of week, which is going to be an integer between 0 and 6.
Where 0 is Sunday and 6 is Saturday. That denotes the day of the week the order was made.
There's going to be an order hour of the day, which is an integer between 0 and 23,
which denotes the hour of the day that the order was made. So 0 would mean that the order was made
between midnight and 1 am. 7 would mean that the order was made between 7 am and 8 am,
etc. And then a day's sense prior order. And this is going to be an integer that represents how many days
it has been since a customer's previous order. So the first order that an individual would make
would have this value be missing, but all subsequent orders they made would be able to reference
how long it has been since that consumer has made an order.
So what's not included here is we don't know anything about the exact date of the transaction
so we understand the order in which the transactions occurred and the amount of time that took
place between each order, but we don't know the year or month or anything else about that.
Additionally, we don't know where these orders were made so we don't know whether this corresponds
to New York City or maybe Austin, Texas or Seattle, Washington. So we have no ability to say
user ID orders in New York City, user ID one orders in New York City while user ID five orders
in Seattle. So we're not going to be able to do that. But let's go ahead and read in this data
and describe it. So let's describe this order's data set. So we see we have about
3 million observations. They're just going to be the days since prior order.
The minimum is zero, which means someone ordered something on a particular day.
They may have forgotten something so they ordered again on the same day.
The maximum number of days between orders is 30. And again, that corresponds to only the
subset of data that is included in the sample. The average time that individuals were ordering was
4 a.m. Oh, sorry, I knew that was funny. So this corresponds to about 13 and a half,
which if we map that into time is about 130 in the afternoon.
And the day of week is about a 2.7, which is most orders are occurring on Wednesday.
It seems and that lines up with this median. So now we have an idea of so we could go ahead and
also look at what's in this data. So we have as we promised an order ID, a user ID,
which order was made. So for example, these are user IDs first five, user ID ones, first five orders.
They ordered one day on a Tuesday, two times on a Wednesday.
And two times on a Thursday, you'll notice it was about it was two weeks and one day
between order one and two. It was three weeks exactly between orders two and three.
Then it was 29 days between orders three and four and 28 days are four weeks between orders four and five.
And this all builds up to the final data set of interest, the order products.
So this can file contains detailed information about each of the orders. So the previous data set
told us some metadata about the orders when they happened, which individual made them,
and now this is going to tell us what was ordered. So the first column is an order ID,
which again is going to allow us to reference the order ID from the previous data set.
There's going to be a product ID, which tells us which product was purchased.
There's going to be an add to cart order. So Instacart is watching the order in which individuals
add items to their cart. And then there's going to be a reordered column. Was this an item that the
individual has ordered in the past so that there it's a reordered item?
Again, what's not included? Importantly, they are not including any information about the price paid
for each product. Let's be precise here for a product. And then they're not telling us the quantity
purchased. So for example, if you bought bananas, they're not telling us did you buy three bananas,
or did you buy seven, they're just saying user ID one purchased 10 bananas.
Okay, so let's talk a little bit more about the relational nature of these files. So as we said,
files and departments provide additional context for the products file.
The products file is then going to describe provide context for the order products that
when we see particular products ordered, we know what products were ordered.
And then orders is going to contain information about win and who made the orders
given in these two files.
So we had IEL, which had an ID, we had department, which had an ID, and these both mapped into the
product, which had an ID, and then told us the IEL ID and the department ID.
Then we had the order status set, which had an
kind of the important information from here was the product name.
Also the name here and the name here. The order is this told us the order ID,
and importantly the user who used it in addition to the win in order was made.
And then finally was what we think is the most important data set here was the ordered
products. And so this mapped into, so this needed an order ID, so that we knew which order we were talking about.
Let's go ahead and box these so that we know these are the different data sets.
Then it told us the product ID that was ordered.
And then it told us the order that items were added to the cart, and whether an item was
re-order or not. But now we're having information about the product come from the product table.
So if we wanted to know the name of a particular product that an individual ordered,
we would need to merge this data in from product. Likewise if we wanted to know which department
or IEL that product came from, we would need to take the data in IEL and department and merge it into
product and then we would take that merged data set and merge it into the order of products.
So let's do a small example about kind of referencing these different data sets.
So Instacart was interested in determining whether certain items or groups of items were re-order
to more than others. So let's explore what items or groups of items were the most re-ordered.
We're going to do this by computing the fraction of re-orders for a particular item or group.
And the way we're going to compute that is we're going to count how many times a particular item was ordered
and what fraction of those orders were a re-order. This isn't a perfect measure,
but we think this is in line with the goals that Instacart had.
So what are we going to do? We're going to take our order product
and so that we're going to take the order product table which has information on what was ordered.
And we're going to merge it with the orders column and in particular we're very interested in the
user ID to know who ordered what. So we'll go ahead and merge this. Again, we're doing a
left so we're only merging in data that is relevant to the order products data frame.
We're going to sort this table by user ID order number and the add-to-cart order
to get an idea of what this data looks like. So we can see that order ID 253 9329
was done by user one. This was user one's first order. You can also see that because there's
no days since their prior order. They had a product ID 196 that they added to the cart
and they added product 14084 all the way to I'm not sure but you can see the structure of this data.
So let's determine which products were the most reordered. So we're going to do this by
selecting the non-nan values of the day-sense prior order. And again, we're doing this
because of this right here. So the first time an individual interacts with the store,
they're not going to be reordering. And so we're going to drop all of the first interactions.
We're then going to group by the product ID. Then we're going to aggregate by counting
the add-to-cart order. So this is just going to give us how many observations there were.
Then we're going to sum reordered because it takes a 0s or 1s. So we know how many
items were reordered. We're only going to work with products that were reordered at least 10 times.
And this is just going to cut out some items that were only reordered once or twice.
We're then going to rename these two columns. So we're going to change add-to-cart order to end order
and reordered to end reorder. We're going to create a new column. This new column is going to be
named a frack reorder for the fraction of orders that were a reorder. And then we're going to
sort this by the fraction of reorders. And then we're going to merge in product information
so that we can see which items are being reordered. So you can see that the
product with the lowest fraction of reorders was about 2%. And the maximum was 100%.
With the median about 50%, the mean about 50%.
Let's look at what this data looks like. So we see the most reorder products were 0pitch nutrient
enhanced water beverage. And Amazake, Almond Shake and Orange Energy Shots.
So I was particularly interested in kind of who is ordering orange energy shots. And so what we did
was remember order product user contains information about the products along with the users
and the orders that were made. So we're going to return to this data frame and we're only going to look at
observations in which orange energy shots, which are product ID 43553, were ordered.
And what we see is let's go ahead and sort, I'll use by order number.
If we wanted to be proper we'd do it by user ID and then order number.
But what you'll see is that there is a single user, user 202 557, who every 10 days on average
or so orders these orange energy shots. So they ordered them on their first order.
They then waited about two weeks. They had two additional orders. So notice this jump
term order 1 to order 4. So in order 2 in 3 they did not order orange energy shots.
And then they ordered again during order 6. So not during order 5 during order 8.
Then order 9. And so once they got started on this product they were ordering them
about every, about once a week. Again we're not seeing the quantity ordered. And so
we're losing in cases like this. There's a question of did the individual purchase
you know, two weeks of orange energy shots. And then just use them over those two weeks
as opposed to here at the end it looks like they were ordering them every couple of days.
But we hope this sets the stage for the data set that we'll be discussing today.