Okay, so we want to compute the average duration of employment.
Well, that's going to be easy.
If we do basically a version of the same calculation that we did before,
we're going to find the average duration of staying employed is now one over beta.
It's exactly the same that we did before,
except in this case, p is going to be beta.
So in our lake model, we have that one over alpha is the average duration of unemployment.
And one over beta is the average duration of employment.
And we got that from just the parameters that define the transition model.
Just mention another example, which is a classic example of a Markov chain.
It's a quite a famous paper by James Hamilton.
For using US unemployment data, so he was looking at unemployment data too.
He estimated a stochastic matrix.
Now you know what that is from our definition.
So he estimated this econometrically.
Later on, we'll talk about how you might go around estimating this.
So he estimated with monthly data, and he had three states.
He had what he called a normal growth state, a mild recession, and a severe recession.
He estimated this some time ago before he actually had data on what we in the United States now regard as severe recessions.
So you know what these transition probabilities are interesting because they tell you like, well, when you're in normal growth, we can just read this.
When you're in normal growth, you usually just stay in the most likely thing is you'll stay in normal growth.
But with a small probability, you'll go into like weak growth.
So you know, if you're in weak growth, the probability is that you'll stay there for next period.
You might go back to normal growth, but there's a very small probability that you'll go to a very bad growth state, big recession.
And if you have the unfortunate to get to a bad growth state, you're never going back from there to high growth right away.
You might transit to a...
Well, if you're not... I'm reading it wrong.
If you're in a very bad growth state, you might recover to a slightly less bad growth state, but you won't go all the way back.
You won't go back here.
So these things that I was just struggling to explain, people write down what's called a directed graph.
And a directed graph has consists of nodes and edges.
It's a very nice way to describe a Markov chain. If you wake up idiot, you'll find that.
So let's see what it looks like.
So this is a typical directed graph to show Hamilton's.
This is Hamilton's model for Markov model for unemployment.
So this is normal growth.
So what this arrow means is with probably...
What this arrow means is you'll just stay next period.
The arrows are one step transition probability, transitions, and the labels are the probabilities.
So you'll stay here. You might go here.
You notice there's no arrow like this.
That would be a different Markov chain.
If you want to get to third state, you're going to have to go through the intermediate state and so on.
Okay.
So just moving ahead.
So to summarize what a Markov chain is going to be a pair.
It's going to be a stochastic matrix.
So this is a marginal distribution over the time zero state.
It's the marginal distribution over the time zero state.
Okay.
So here's...
This is kind of a key sentence.
So one way to study questions about Markov chains is just to simulate them.
And big parts of statistics actually do this.
They take Markov chains and they simulate them to learn things actually about the chain.
So this...
We're going to spend some time talking about this bullet point.
There's a lot in here. To approximate the probability of an event E.
What you can do is you can run a simulation many times and then you count fractions.
Okay. So do you remember...
We spent some time talking about what this probability mean.
So what a frequentist thinks that what probability means is the fraction
that can be anticipated in a very large sample.
And that's being exploited right here.
Here's some advertisement.
There's...
If you go to Quanticon, we've written Python programs that make it very easy for you to study and simulate Markov chains.
So what we're going to...
What this...
So the Quanticon team did the work for you there.
But it's actually...
Markov chains are so fun and interesting to get your hands on.
What this lecture does is it backs up and actually from scratch using NumPy, it's going to...
It's going to generate some...
It's going to show you how to simulate a Markov chain.
So let's spend a little time talking about that.
And then in your time, I think this is a great way to learn Python and build your confidence is...
Do this too and do some examples.
So here's how to make your own.
The first thing we need is we have to have a Markov chain.
What I called Pi0 here, we're going to call this...
We're going to call this...
Whatever that word is psi.
So a Markov chain is going to be a P psi pair.
It's going to be P psi in root and P psi in root.
It's going to be a P psi in root and P psi in root.
So this is the time.
So if you give it one...
That's the time.
So that's the time...
So if you give me those two, you define a Markov chain.
them state from the marginal distribution at time zero. And then every subsequent time
period we're going to draw the new state from the transition probability matrix. So this
is the initial and this is transitions and that's how we're going to use it. So you know
to make to make this go we need one more thing. We need a P, a psi and we need a random
number generator. So and we're going to use we're going to use a something from quanticon.
So so this cell code is actually describing how that's done. An example would be here's
here's the language. Here's the language. This I think it's really good to slowly read Python code.
It's good for your character. It's good for mine. That's a line that says that generates a
distribution that I want. So we talked about this earlier like if I give you a probability
distribution how can you generate a random draw from it. Well this is how quanticon is going
to do it. So I start with the probability distribution psi right here and then that's what I want.
I want to accumulate a distribution function. So what I'm now going to just that's just a
numpy command. I'm going to compute the cumulative distribution and then what quanticon do is
quant quanticon dot random dot draw CDF of I'm going to draw from this CDF a random draw and it
tells me give me five numbers. And my five numbers is going to give me well there I drew a
jiu success success success success failure. So did you. Okay so that's we're going to use that.
So we have our three things we have a P we have a psi and we have a random number generator. And
now we're all dressed up and ready to go. So we're going to this quanticon code in this little
thing we're going to write as the casting matrix P. We're going to need an initial state. And we're
going to take a sample size. So what I want you to do is study this on your own because now we're
quote unquote rolling our own. We're writing Python function that's going to that's going to generate a
a sample path of length. Well you're going to make this up because there's these a key word
arguments. We're going to make this up. We're going to input a P and we're going to input a
an initial condition, an initial distribution. And then we're going to do a sample size. So here we go.
So here's how we here's how this works. Just just an example. We'll take this mark off chain.
Here's a claim. That's what does probability mean again? We're cycling back to that idea.
And this is a claim. This is a reminder and a claim that this is going to be verified.
So well we're going to verify it very soon. That's the claim. What does probability mean?
That's our classic question. So what we're going to do is we're going to use this code.
X is going to be we're going to generate how many 100,000. You try that on your machine.
There's our mark off chain. We're going to try it from this initial distribution.
And we're going to generate a very long chain. And then the claim here in this lecture is that
the sample mean is going to be a mean for this for a very long sample is going to be around 0.25.
And notice when we generated this and then we used numpy to actually compute the mean.
And it turns out to be very close to 0.25. Now, let me make a claim. It's going to make
a somewhat serious claim before I kind of pause this what we're talking about. I claim
that if you compute the left eigenvectors of this matrix, that matrix, left eigenvector,
associated, I'll put a I'm going to take the left eigenvector of that matrix associated with
the unit eigenvalue. So I'm claiming that this matrix has a unit eigenvalue.
You could do this in next size. If you take the left eigenvector of that and you normalize it,
then you will compute, I'm going to say something called the stationary distribution
of the chain. Now, this is kind of mysterious. And then I could take the stationary distribution.
I haven't told you what a stationary distribution is yet. When I'm telling you take this matrix,
take the left eigenvector associated with the unit eigenvalue.
The left eigenvalue, that's equal to the right eigenvector of the matrix P transpose.
So if you take that and you normalize it, meaning the probability is sum to 1. So it sums to 1.
Normalize it so it sums to 1. You're going to get something that I'm going to call the
stationary distribution, which I haven't defined. And then if you compute the mean of x at the
stationary distribution, that's going to be equal to 0.25.
At this point, we could kind of leave this as an exercise, maybe for me and maybe for you.
So what do we need to do? We have to use numpy linear algebra to compute the eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
And then we're just about done to verify this.
OK, we're going to pause, take a break for a little bit now. Thank you.