Okay, so now we are ready for our lead example of a Markov chain, something that we really
want to talk about, the economics and statistics of.
So this is going to be a version of a famous model called the Lake Model of, in our instance,
unemployment, but it could be some, a lake model of other things.
So we are going to consider a worker who at any given time T is either unemployed and
we will call that state zero, if he is unemployed, or is employed state one.
So, employed means he or she has a job, unemployed means doesn't have a job, but is looking
for a job.
And suppose that over one month, if you are an unemployed worker, you find a job with
probability alpha.
So alpha equals the probability that an unemployed worker finds a job with his next draw.
But an employed worker could become, so basically we have an unemployed worker could switch
to become an employed worker with a probability alpha.
But an employed worker sometimes becomes unemployed with probability beta.
So in terms of our Markov model, we are going to have the state space, here we go.
S equals zero one, there we go.
The transition probability, we go from zero to one with probability alpha.
We go from one to zero with probability beta.
And then because the row sums have to sum to one, we automatically can fill in the whole
matrix.
So this is our first stochastic matrix.
And if I supplement that with some probability of your employment state, let's call the
employment state, x t, if I supplement at times zero, if I supplement that with a probability
of distribution, which would look like this, let's say, I'll just make this up.
I'll call it pi zero, it's just a matrix.
So let's say it's a 20% chance you're unemployed and 80% chance that you're employed at times
zero, I'm just making this up.
Then the pair, pi zero, that is a Markov chain.
And that Markov chain generates a probability distribution over our entire sequence, an entire
infinite sequence of the random variable employed versus unemployed.
So our random variable would take two values, zero or one.
And so a history of a person might look like starts out at times zero being unemployed,
unemployed, finds a job, stays in the job, stays in the job, stays in the job, stays in the
job, gets fired, stays unemployed.
So this sequence, going on forever, describes the life history of the worker.
So if we know the values of alpha and beta, we can ask all sorts of questions.
We could ask what's the average duration of unemployment?
We could ask over a long horizon, what's the fraction of time that a worker finds yourself
unemployed?
We could say conditional unemployment, what is the probability of becoming unemployed, at
least once, over the next 12 months?
That's a complicated event, but we could figure that out.
And that's going to be useful.
I want to take a little detour now and show you some properties of a geometric
distribution, an important distribution.
So here's why we do this in a minute.
The geometric distribution is, this is going to be a random variable.
And we're going to let p be the probability of what we're going to call success.
And one minus p be the probability of failure.
This is actually one to Bernoulli trial.
That's all this is.
And now what we're going to do is we're just going to repeat.
We're going to take a sequence of independent Bernoulli trials.
And we're going to form a certain random variable, which I'm going to tell you about.
And the random variable we're interested is this.
It's the times in a sequence of Bernoulli trials.
It's the time before we get one success.
So I'm going to take a sequence of draws.
And I want to know the probability of k failures, the probability of k failures, before the
first success.
And k is going to be go from 0, 1, 2, onto infinity.
And I'm going to let yi be the value of the random variable success of failure in the
Ith trial.
So if I just take a sequence of Bernoulli trials, I'm just going to get a sequence of 0s or
1s.
So I want to compute this probability.
So here goes.
Let's compute it.
Well, I want to compute, I just go, I do not skip steps.
I write down what I want to compute.
I want this, the probability that y equals 0, y1 equals 0, y1 equals 0, yk1 minus 1 equals
0.
Finally, this is my first one occurs at the kth trial.
I want to compute the probability of this.
This is what I want to compute.
And I know that my draws are independent.
They're independent.
Why?
Because I'm assuming it.
OK, so now I just write down, I use independence.
The probability of this is of that, that's a joint distribution.
No, that's a joint distribution.
I want to compute, that's a probability that comes from the joint distribution.
I now use independence.
So the joint distribution is just the product of the marginal distributions.
That's independence.
So I write that down.
So that's just the probability y0 equals 0, probability y1 equals 0, dot, dot, dot, probability
yk minus 1 equals 0.
Finally, times probability yk equals 1.
Now I just copy.
Well, this is equal to 1 minus p, where I got that from here.
This is equal to 1 minus p again, 1 minus p k times, and then finally, p.
Get that from here.
Isn't that beautiful?
And then I just collect.
So that's equal to this, 1 minus p k times p.
So when I set up the draws like that, how long do I have to wait?
That's the probability.
So this is a probability, that's a probability distribution.
And it's a waiting time.
It's called a waiting time.
It's a time to my first success.
And it is called a geometric distribution.
Well, why?
Why is it called a geometric distribution?
Well, it's because of this factor, 1 minus p raised to the k.
That's a geometric series.
So this is called a geometric series.
And then it's just normalized so the probabilities add up to 1.
So we'll note this.
You calculate summation 1 minus p to the k times p.
Sum that up.
Use your high school knowledge of geometric series.
We get 1.
So now we could calculate the expected time to first success.
And this has a name, expected time to first success.
This is called expected waiting time.
We're going to use this in a minute in this lecture, in a really fun way.
So if you just calculate that now, this is a little tricky to calculate.
Well, we calculate the expected time.
I'm just going to calculate the mean.
How do I calculate a mean?
I take summation k, goes from 0 to infinity.
Those are all the values.
I multiply the values of the random variable times the probability, which I just
read off from my probability distribution.
If you sum those up, I'm not going to derive this here.
But if you sum this up, you can check it on a computer.
This is just equal to 1 over p.
So 1 over p is the expected waiting time for a geometric distribution.
And we're going to see why I did that right now.
So let's return to where we were before.
And we have this quote unquote lake model we were talking about.
We have this Markov chain.
And the probability, if we come back up here,
the probability that an unemployed worker moves into employment
is in any given period, the probability of success, the probability of a success,
is alpha.
I will call that a success.
We'll call the failure as the person stays unemployed.
So what we can read right from this is the expected waiting time.
Here is just 1 over alpha.
That's 1 over alpha.
So that's the expected duration.
That's the average duration of unemployment.
That's the average duration of unemployment for an unemployed worker who
fits this model.
And now we can come up here as success is just a definition.
We have an employed worker going the other way.
An employed worker here, a quote unquote success.
It's a bad word now in this sense.
Success is the employed worker becomes unemployed.
Well, we have a waiting time distribution.
So if we do a calculation, what's the average duration of employment?
Well, this will turn out to be, it won't be this.
We could figure that out.
So the average duration of, yeah.
So I'm going to ask you to figure that out as an exercise.
Maybe I'll stop this now and ask what's the average duration of employment.
How long do you keep a job?
That's an interesting number.
It's going to depend on data.
And we'll be able to calculate that.
So why don't you work on that?
And I'll work on it for a minute.