Hi, this is Tom and today I'm going to talk with you about finite dimensional Markov
chains.
And my text for this, for which I'm going to basically provide a reader's guide, is
the Quanticon lecture on Markov chains, which is on the Quanticon website.
Okay, so what basically the roadmap is we're going to define a Markov chain, see how to
construct it, talk about simulations, and we'll construct marginal distribution.
And then we'll talk about these concepts of irreducibility and nonperiodic Markov chains.
And those are going to be important because of how they relate to stationary distributions.
We'll talk about the concept of stationary distributions, this notion of stationarity
and air-godicity.
We'll talk about those, and we'll talk about how to approximate expectations.
And so let's get rolling.
Okay, so what you're going to find is a Markov chain is just widely used in economics,
finance, machine learning, actually encryption.
And it's the workhorse of building dynamic models with this, some randomness.
So there are as powerful as they are, we already have the tools to study them.
The key tools are going to be a little bit of linear algebra and basic probability theory.
So this lecture is accompanied by a notebook, which you would be able to run at Jupiter notebook.
So as usual, here's our Quanticon, various things we download.
We import if we're going to be using Python as we are.
Okay, so we'll just start with some definitions.
Key definitions, key notion is there's going to be a matrix, and it's going to be a stochastic matrix.
It's p, we'll call it p, and it's an n by n, so it's a square matrix.
Each element, P i j, is strictly positive.
Well, actually non-negative, we'll see non-negative, because it's going to be a probability.
And this is going to be a conditional probability.
So it's a matrix full of conditional probabilities, and each the row sums, so if we sum across for every row, this is going to be one.
So each row of peak is a probability distribution in itself.
It's itself a probability distribution over n possible outcomes, because j goes from one to n.
And we're going to talk about what these mean.
And we call this a stochastic matrix if it satisfies one and two.
So that's how to read that.
So it's worthwhile staring at that.
So we have a set of non-negative matrices.
It's implied by this. This actually implies these two things will imply that p i j,
itself, is a probability. It's some number less than or equal to one greater than or equal to zero.
That's for all i j. So each element of the matrix is a probability.
And what you can find is, this is what this, if p is a stochastic matrix, is a stochastic matrix, that implies
p to the k is also for any k greater than or equal to one.
Well actually, greater, yeah, greater than or equal to one.
Okay.
So that's what it's matrix is.
So a stochastic matrix is, it's a key thing that it's a big part of a Markov chain.
So one thing to define a Markov chain, to define a Markov chain, we need a stochastic matrix p plus something else.
And we'll see what that something else is.
So to begin with, we're going to define some set of elements, x1 through xn.
And we're going to call that a state space.
And these are the state values.
So that's what the set is.
So the Markov chain is defined on a state space s.
And what it is, it's a sequence of random variables.
So it's a sequence of random variables.
On s, that have something called the Markov property.
The key thing is what the Markov property is.
And the Markov property is something about conditional probabilities.
It's a restriction on conditional probabilities.
So here goes.
We're going to have the way we're going to do this is x at t is the random variable,
it's a member of this sequence at t.
And it could possibly take on various values.
It's going to take on some value.
It's going to take on a value inside this set, the x1 through x.
So the Markov property is this.
It's that the probability that xt plus 1 is equal to a particular value y,
condition on xt, that random variable, is equal to the probability that it takes on the value y,
condition on not only xt, but past values of xt.
So only xt carries information about future values of the random variable x.
So stare at this.
And this is intimately connected with this is the reason why we give this name xt is the state of xt.
Xt is the state variable.
It completely summarizes the current position of the system.
Lagged values don't add any information.
So we could write this.
The probability, if we write the probability of xt plus 1 is equal to y,
given xt equals x.
As we write that, this is matrix of p of xy for all xy and s.
That's going to give rise to a matrix.
And what this means is pxy is the probability of going from x to y in one unit of time, one step.
So this is the one step transition probability.
That's what this is called.
So one step transition probability.
And actually, if we go back to where we started, these pijs, those are just the one step transition probabilities from going from i to j.
So here we go.
Pij is the probability that we go from xy to xj in one step.
And the i's and j's both go from one to n. That fills out our matrix.
So here's how we, to complete, to complete a description of a Markov chain, we need p.
And we also need something else.
We need a probability over states at time equals zero.
We need this pair.
And a Markov chain is going to be, it's going to consist of that pair.
And the way we can generate wealth.
So what this says is we're going to draw x0 from some initial distribution, from this distribution.
And then for each subsequent t, we're going to draw xt plus one from the transition to probability.
So this is how a Markov chain works.